<section id="gui.toolwindows.grids"><title>Grids Window</title>
	<indexterm><primary>GUI</primary><secondary>tool windows</secondary><tertiary>grids</tertiary></indexterm>
	
	<para>
		<inlinegraphic fileref="images/stack_surfaces.png"/>Grids Window
	</para>
	
	<figure><title>Grids Window</title>
		<graphic fileref="images/window_grids.png" align="center"/>
	</figure>

	<para>The Grids Tool Window provides management for grid data sets owned by the different models. All grid data sets held by the current model are displayed here, and. The appearance of individual grids may be changed, and axes / cutoffs changed. Grid data can also be cut, copied, and pasted to different models.</para>

	<section><title>General Grid Management</title>
		<para>Each grid in the left-hand list has associated with it a checkbox that determines whether or not it is currently visible. Below the list the minimum and maximum data values contained within the grid, and the current cutoff (i.e. the value that the isosurface is drawn at) to use when rendering the data. The File and Edit menus allow to load new grids into the current model, and to cut, paste, and delete grids between models.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>Data Manipulation</title>
		<para>The associated origin and axes to the currently selected grid may be modified in the top-right panel. In this way grid data may be arbitrarily flipped, stretched, and sheared, and its position in the local space of the model changed. All changes made are reflected immediately in the main view.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>Appearance</title>
		<para>The style of the selected grid can be modified in the lower-right panel, with the general rendering style set with the combo box (see <link linkend="enums.gridstyles">grid styles</link> for a list of possible styles).</para>
	
		<para>For grids in which the data is 'symmetric' about a cutoff of zero (as is the case for orbital data, for example) the 'Symm' checkbox should be ticked to inform Aten that both the normal surface (above the cutoff) and the negative surface (below the negative of the cutoff) should be drawn.</para>
	</section>

	<section><title>Colouring</title>
		<para>In the simplest case the points, triangles, or polygons that make up the rendered grid data are drawn in a single colour. This colour is determined by the upper of the two colour selections. If the data is symmetric (see above) and is composed of 'positive' and 'negative' parts, then the uppermost colour selection is applied to the positive part, and the lower colour selection is applied to the negative part. In addition, the transparency of the rendered data (if drawn in the Solid style) is determined by the Alpha value (0.0 being fully transparent, and 1.0 being fully opaque).</para>

		<para>Should a more useful colouring scheme be desired than the grid may be rendered using a <link linkend="topics.colourscales">colour scale</link>, in which case the isovalue (if volumetric) or height (if a 2D grid) determines the colour of the data point. To do so, enable the checkbox next to the CScale widget, and select the ID of the colour scale to use (from the ten definable in the program).</para>
	</section>

</section>
