<section id="tutorials.alumina"><title>Building &#952;-Alumina from Basic Crystal Data</title>
	<indexterm><primary>building</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>alumina</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>crystals</primary></indexterm>
	<indexterm><primary>cell manipulation</primary></indexterm>

	<para>Crystal structures are useful for many things, provided you can find them in electronic format. When you can't and are left with the bare crystallographic data in a paper things are slightly more troublesome. This was exactly my experience when working with &#952;-alumina -- the crystal information is readily available in Zhou and Snyder, <emphasis>Acta. Cryst. B</emphasis>, vol 47, p617 (1991), but no 3D coordinates were floating around on the interweb. Here's how I made use of it...</para>
	
	<sect5><title>1. Create the Unit Cell and add Symmetry Unique Atoms</title>
		<para>First, we create the crystal cell in which to add our atoms. From the paper we see it is a monoclinic cell with &#946; = 103.83&deg;, and side lengths <emphasis>A</emphasis> = 11.854, <emphasis>B</emphasis> = 2.904, and <emphasis>C</emphasis> = 5.622 &#197;. You may want to zoom out afterwards to get a proper look at the new cell.</para>
		
		<para>There a five symmetry-unique atoms to add into the cell, which will in turn be used to generate the remaining 35 symmetry-related atoms to give the complete unit cell. To add the atoms we will use the Add Atom method in the editing tools. Atom positions in the paper are given in fractional coordinates - we will create the atoms using these coordinates which will be converted to their 'real' equivalents by Aten (according to the current cell) as we add them.</para>

		<table frame='all' pgwide='1' tocentry='0'>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/stack_celledit.png"/></entry>
						<entry>Open the Cell Edit window</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>Add a unit cell to the model by checking the 'Has Cell?' checkbox.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>Set the cell lengths <emphasis>A</emphasis>, <emphasis>B</emphasis>, and <emphasis>C</emphasis> to 11.854, 2.904, and 5.622 respectively.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>Set the cell angle &#946; to 103.83&deg;.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><emphasis>Build Toolbar</emphasis></entry>
						<entry>On the Build toolbar change the active element to aluminium by clicking the <inlinegraphic fileref="images/build_element.png"/> button and selecing it in the periodic table.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/stack_build.png"/></entry>
						<entry>Open the Build window</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>
							<para>On the Add Atom page make sure the fractional coordinates ('Frac?') checkbox is checked and then enter the following sets of coordinates, clicking 'Add' after each set is entered:</para>
							<para>x = 0.6595, y = 0.0, z = 0.3165</para>
							<para>x = 0.9166, y = 0.0, z = 0.2073</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><emphasis>Build Toolbar</emphasis></entry>
						<entry>On the Build toolbar change the active element to oxygen by clicking the <inlinegraphic fileref="images/build_element.png"/> button and selecting it in the periodic table.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>
							<para>Enter the following sets of coordinates in the Build window, clicking 'Add' after each set:</para>
							<para>x = 0.8272, y = 0.0, z = 0.4273</para>
							<para>x = 0.495, y = 0.0, z = 0.2526</para>
							<para>x = 0.1611, y = 0.0, z = 0.0984</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		
		<figure><title>Addition of symmetry-unique atoms</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/tutorial_alumina1.png" align="center"/>
		</figure>

	</sect5>

	<sect5><title>2. Assign the Spacegroup and Pack</title>
		
		<para>To complete the model the spacegroup of the crystal must be set, so that generation of the symmetry-related atoms can be performed. This is all done on the Cell page. The spacegroup can be entered as either its numeric ID (as listed in the IUC Tables) or as the unformatted spacegroup name - &#952;-alumina belongs to spacegroup C2/m (number 12). Symmetry-related copies of the five atoms present in the cell are then generated by selecting Pack. Any overlapping atoms resulting from the application of the spacegroup's generators are automatically removed.</para>

		<table frame='all' pgwide='1' tocentry='0'>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/stack_celledit.png"/></entry>
						<entry>Open the Cell Edit window again</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>Enter the spacegroup as "C2/m" or "12" and press 'Set' to assign the spacegroup to the model</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>Generate symmetry equivalent atoms by pressing the 'Pack' button</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		
		<figure><title>Fully-packed crystal</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/tutorial_alumina2.png" align="center"/>
		</figure>

	</sect5>

	<sect5><title>3. Replicate Cell and Calculate Bonds</title>
		
		<para>The basic crystal unit of &#952;-alumina isn't too interesting on its own, so lets create a chunk to properly see the structure. Replicate the unit cell by 3 or 4 units in each positive direction (or more if you're feeling adventurous) and then calculate the bonding in the model.</para>
		
		<table frame='all' pgwide='1' tocentry='0'>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry><inlinegraphic fileref="images/stack_celltransform.png"/></entry>
						<entry>Open the Cell Transform window</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>On the Replicate page set each positive replication direction to 3 or 4</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry></entry>
						<entry>Generate the supercell by pressing the 'Replicate' button</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><emphasis>Bonding Toolbar</emphasis></entry>
						<entry>On the Bonding toolbar recalculate bonds with <inlinegraphic fileref="images/bond_calc.png"/></entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		
		<figure><title>Replicated and rebonded superlattice</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/tutorial_alumina3.png" align="center"/>
		</figure>
		
	</sect5>

	<sect5><title>Script</title>
		
		<programlisting>
newmodel("alumina");
cell(11.854, 2.904, 5.622, 90, 103.83, 90);
newatomfrac(Al,0.6595,0,0.3165);
newatomfrac(Al,0.9166,0,0.2073);
newatomfrac(O,0.8272,0,0.4272);
newatomfrac(O,0.495,0,0.2526);
newatomfrac(O,0.1611,0,0.0984);
spacegroup("C2/m");
pack();
replicate(0,0,0,3,3,3);
rebond();
		</programlisting>

	</sect5>

</section>
