<chapter id="installation"><title>Installation</title>

<para>Whether installing from a pre-built package or running 'make install' (or not) after building it yourself, there are several resources which Aten needs or expects to find. The most important of these is the default library of filters without which nothing can be loaded or saved (but note that this does not prevent Aten from running). Then there's the optional user preferences file, and finally the optional user filter library. If Aten was installed from a package or built and 'make install'ed yourself then the default filters should be located correctly when Aten runs withour further intervention (if not, read on). No user preferences file is created or installed, and must be created either through the GUI or edited by hand.</para>

<section id="installation.filters"><title>Filters</title>

<para>As already mentioned, Aten comes with a selection of filters ready to import and export a fair number of file formats (you can write your own - see the chapter on <link linkend="filters">Filters</link>). These filters should be found automatically, but if they are not Aten can be given their location in one of two ways:</para>

<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Through the environment variable ATENDATA</term>
		<listitem><para>On all systems, the environment variable <filename>ATENDATA</filename> can be set with the full path to the 'data' directory which contains the filters directory.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>With the command-line argument --atendata</term>
		<listitem><para>In a similar manner, the <filename>--atendata</filename> command-line argument can be used to provide the full path to the 'data' directory which contains the filters directory.</para></listitem>
	</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</section>

<section id="installation.userfilters"><title>User Filters</title>
<para>Any filters written or obtained by the used can be placed in their <filename>~/.aten/filters</filename> directory. See the <link linkend="installation.dotaten">next section</link>
</section>

<section id="installation.dotaten"><title>The ~/.aten Directory</title>
<para>User filters and preferences files should be placed in a <filename>.aten</filename> directory in your home directory (it must be created by hand).  Within this directory can exist the user preferences file <filename>prefs.dat</filename> exists, along with another directory named <filename>filters</filename> which is used to store custom filters, or those currently under development by the user.
</section>

</chapter>
