<section id="compilation"><title>Compilation From Source</title>
	
	<para>If you want to compile Aten by hand (e.g. if you're keeping your own copy of the source and updating it <emphasis>via</emphasis> subversion) then these guides may help.</para>
	
	<section id="compilation.linux"><title>Linux</title>
	
		<para>Very few Linux distributions have guides in this section - if you wish to contribute details of your own experience for the benefit of others, get in touch.</para>
		
		<section id="compilation.linux.suse"><title>SuSE</title>
		
			<section><title>Installing Subversion and obtaining the source</title>
		
				<para>TODO</para>
				
			</section>
		
		</section>
			
		<section id="compilation.linux.ubuntu"><title>Ubuntu (9.04)</title>
		
			<section><title>Installing Subversion and obtaining the source</title>
			
				<para>Run the following commands to install subversion (if you don't already have it) and download the latest source to a directory names 'aten-latest' in the current directory:</para>
			
				<synopsis>
				bob@pc:~> sudo apt-get install subversion
				bob@pc:~> svn co http://aten.googlecode.com/svn/trunk ./aten-latest
				bob@pc:~> cd aten-latest
				</synopsis>
			
			</section>
			
			<section><title>Installing all necessary pre-requisites</title>
			
				<para>The following command should install all necessary packages needed to compile Aten, including the Qt4 development libraries, C++ (g++) compiler, and the automake/libtool packages.</para>
			
				<synopsis>
				bob@pc:> sudo apt-get install autotools-dev libtool autoconf automake g++ libreadline5-dev libqt4-gui libqt4-opengl libqt4-core libqt4-dev
				</synopsis>
			
			</section>
			
			<section><title>Configure and compile</title>
			
				<para>Configure the source with the following commands, run from the 'aten-latest' directory:</para>
			
				<synopsis>
				bob@pc:> ./autogen.sh
				bob@pc:> ./configure
				</synopsis>
				
				<para>All being well, no errors should be encountered by the configure script. If there are any and you have problems, please email me!</para>
				
				<para>Once succesfully configured, build the source with:</para>
				
				<synopsis>
				bob@pc:> make
				</synopsis>
			
			</section>
			
		</section>
		
		<section id="compilation.mac"><title>Mac</title>
		
			<section><title>Prerequisites</title>
			
				<para>GNU Autotools >=2.6 or CMake >=2.4.8 - the choice is yours, really. CMake tends to be easier because it handles all the Qt-related elements explicitly, but a pretty recent version is required. Follow the relevant sections below.</para>
				
				<para>Qt4 >=4.2 - again, two choices. Trolltech offer an installable disk image, providing Qt4 as a proper Framework (see http://trolltech.com/products/appdev/platform/qt-for-mac ). Alternatively, Qt4 is available on Fink (qt4-x11).</para>
				
				<para>OpenGL - This __should__ be installed as standard.</para>
				
				<para>pkg-config - If you're using the Fink installation of Qt4, then you'll also need the pkg-config package from the same source (package name?).</para>
				
				<para>A C++ compiler (e.g. GNU g++, Intel's icc)</para>
			
			</section>
		
			<section><title>Autotools</title>
			
				<para>If you obtained the source via ((SVN)), at the top of the source tree run:</para>
				
				<synopsis>
				bob@pc~> ./autogen.sh
				</synopsis>
				
				<para>This creates the necessary files needed to properly configure the build. If you unpacked the source from a tarball, it shouldn't be necessary to run autogen.sh, but you could if unexpected other errors occur in a last ditch attempt to remedy the situation.</para>
				
				<para>Run ./configure to set up the build. The default installation location can be overridden by specifying ./configure --prefix=&lt;path&gt;. It will be necessary to specify which Qt4 installation you have (Framework or Fink).</para>
				
				<para>If using the installed Framework from Trolltech, run:</para>
				
				<synopsis>
				bob@pc~> ./configure --with-qt=framework
				</synopsis>
				
				<para>If using the Fink installation, run:</para>
				
				<synopsis>
				bob@pc~> ./configure --with-qt=fink
				</synopsis>
				
				<para>With the Fink installation you may also need to direct ./configure.ac to the correct Qt4 development binaries either by setting your $PATH to '/sw/lib/qt4-x11/bin:${PATH}' or by running:</para>
				
				<synopsis>
				bob@pc~> ./configure --with-qt=fink --with-qtdir=path
				</synopsis>
				
				<para>...where 'path' is the path where the development binaries can be found.</para>
				
				<para>Once configured successfully, run 'make' to compile the source and build the program. Then, go make some tea or brew some coffee.</para>
			
			</section>
		
			<section><title>CMake</title>
			
				<para>An out-of-tree build is best. Make a directory somewhere, enter in to it, and run:</para>
				
				<synopsis>
				bob@pc~> cmake /path/to/source/for/aten
				</synopsis>
				
				<para>For example:</para>
				
				<synopsis>
				bob@pc:> mkdir aten-build
				bob@pc:> cd aten-build
				bob@pc:~/aten-build> cmake /home/bob/aten-0.99-713
				</synopsis>
				
				<para>Once configured successfully, run 'make' to compile the source and build the program. Then, go make some tea or brew some coffee.</para>
				
			</section>
		
		</section>
		
	</section>
	
</section>
